<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Bill Kidwell</title>
    <link>http://bill-kidwell.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Bill Kidwell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>kidwell.bill&#43;site@gmail.com (Bill Kidwell)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>kidwell.bill&#43;site@gmail.com (Bill Kidwell)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 21:21:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bill-kidwell.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>why blog?</title>
      <link>http://bill-kidwell.github.io/post/2016-06-23-why-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 21:21:13 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>kidwell.bill&#43;site@gmail.com (Bill Kidwell)</author>
      <guid>http://bill-kidwell.github.io/post/2016-06-23-why-blog/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps blogs still have a purpose today, and perhaps they do not. Only time will tell. My purpose in setting this site is to begin writing again, and to share some things I learn with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-it-come-to-this&#34;&gt;How did it come to this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My career has been a long, busy road. As soon as I started my professional life I also started taking graduate courses. I had promised myself when I was working on my B.S. that if I still enjoyed school when I finished, I would look at graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered going straight to grad school, but the payoff was just not there.  A Master&amp;rsquo;s degree didn&amp;rsquo;t earn you much more without experience.  So, I decided my best course was to work on it part time.  I started working on my Master&amp;rsquo;s degree, but later switched to work on my Ph.D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a number of setbacks and breaks along the way.  We moved, I changed jobs, there were family situations, etc&amp;hellip; Getting your Ph.D. is difficult.  Getting it while working full time is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; difficult. But persistence pays off, and here I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you finish a journey like that, it is a huge relief, and generally a good time to take a break. When I was in school, I was generally busy with coursework, conducting research, or otherwise occupied. I tried to start up blogs several times in that period, but it was difficult to keep a rhythm. After all, you are trying to contribute something to the research community.  That is pretty significant, and when that is your goal, it overshadows options like blogging &amp;ndash; or at least it did for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;now-what&#34;&gt;Now what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the break has ended. I am in a good rhythm with work, the family, and ready to start writing and sharing. Hopefully it proves useful to someone out there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>